<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Home on VB Wiki</title>
    <link>https://wiki.victorbilgin.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Home on VB Wiki</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://wiki.victorbilgin.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://wiki.victorbilgin.com/docs/books/facebook/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://wiki.victorbilgin.com/docs/books/facebook/</guid>
      <description>Facebook - Steven Levy #  Review #  I enjoyed this book and would recommend it if you&amp;rsquo;re looking for any of the below:
 An in-depth look at Facebook from the beginning until ~2019 An in-depth look at Mark Zuckerberg An understanding of how Facebook operates as an organization and a business  In terms of the writing, I felt like Levy jumped around chronologically to the point of confusion in certain chapters.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://wiki.victorbilgin.com/docs/books/permanent-record/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://wiki.victorbilgin.com/docs/books/permanent-record/</guid>
      <description>Permanent Record - Edward Snowden #  Review #  An insightful look into the mind of a whistleblower. Regardless of your political opinion, I think it’s hard to underestimate Snowden. He’s cunning, down-to-earth, and caring. This is also a truly mind-bending look at the guts of the American (and in some ways global) intelligence community. It’s like looking at a slaughterhouse right before eating a steak. And by that I mean it made me gag when I saw the innards of intelligence.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://wiki.victorbilgin.com/docs/linux/linux-journey/advanced-text-fu/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://wiki.victorbilgin.com/docs/linux/linux-journey/advanced-text-fu/</guid>
      <description>Advanced Text-Fu #  regex (regular expressions) #   powerful tool for pattern recognition  Test string: sally sells seashells by the seashore  beginning of a line:^by will match by the seashore end of a line: seashore$ will match by the seashore match a single character: b. will match by bracket notation: match characters in the brackets  d[iou]g will match dig, dog, dug ^ in bracket means anything besides this: d[^i]g will match dog and dug but not dig specify a range of characters with a -: d[a-c]g brackets are case sensitive    </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://wiki.victorbilgin.com/docs/linux/linux-journey/command-line/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://wiki.victorbilgin.com/docs/linux/linux-journey/command-line/</guid>
      <description>Command Line #  The Shell #   shell is just a program that takes your commands from the keyboard and sends them to the OS many types of shells: bash (bourne again shell), ksh, zsh, tsch echo will print the argument(s) to the screen date will print the current date whoami will print the currently logged in user&amp;rsquo;s username  pwd (Print Working Directory) #   everything in Linux is a file use pwd to see where you are currently located in the directory structure - the path  cd (change directory) #   you can specifiy paths in two ways: relative and absolute the absolute way means you type the path from the root directory / onward relative means you can use these shortcuts in the path since they are relative to where you currently are:  .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://wiki.victorbilgin.com/docs/linux/linux-journey/permissions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://wiki.victorbilgin.com/docs/linux/linux-journey/permissions/</guid>
      <description>Permissions #  file permissions #   long listing for a file example: drwxr-xr-x 2 pete penguins 4096 Dec 1 11:45 file.txt four main parts to file&amp;rsquo;s permissions: drwxr-xr-x  first is the type of file (d for dir and - for regular file) next three are groups of three bits that denote actual permissions: rwx, r-x, and r-x  these represent the user permissions, group permissions, and other permissions r: readable w: writable x: executable (an executable program) -: empty      modifying permissions #   use chmod with + or - to add or remove permissions for example: chmod u+x myfile means to add the execute bit to the user permissions for myfile change multiple permission bits: chmod ug+w myfile will add writable bit to both user and group permissions using numerical syntax:  4: read 2: write 1: exec   chmod 755 myfile will provide all permissions to user but only read and exec to group and other permissions  ownership permissions #   you can change the user and group ownership of a file as well user: sudo chown &amp;lt;username&amp;gt; &amp;lt;file/dir&amp;gt; group: sudo chgrp &amp;lt;group&amp;gt; &amp;lt;file/dir&amp;gt; both: sudo shown &amp;lt;user&amp;gt;:&amp;lt;group&amp;gt; &amp;lt;file/dir&amp;gt;  umask #   every file gets created with certain default permissions use umask to change those default permissions umask takes the numerical permission syntax but not added: umask 021  we say what we want to take away so for the above example we would take no bits away from users take write bit away from group and take way exec from other   this won&amp;rsquo;t persist past a restart; need to modify .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://wiki.victorbilgin.com/docs/linux/linux-journey/text-fu/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://wiki.victorbilgin.com/docs/linux/linux-journey/text-fu/</guid>
      <description>Text-Fu #  stdout (standard out) #   echo hello world &amp;gt; peanuts.txt processes in linux use i/o streams to receive input and return output normally, echo takes the input (stdin) from the keyboard and returns the output (stdout) to the screen i/o redirection allows us to redirect the output to a file or another command: &amp;gt; if a file doesn&amp;rsquo;t already exist, it will create it. if it does exist, it will overwrite it &amp;gt;&amp;gt; to append instead of overwrite  stdin (standard in) #   the usual source for stdin is the keyboard but we can also use files, output from other processes, and the terminal &amp;lt; for stdin redirection cat &amp;lt; peanuts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://wiki.victorbilgin.com/docs/linux/linux-journey/user-management/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://wiki.victorbilgin.com/docs/linux/linux-journey/user-management/</guid>
      <description>User Management #  users and groups #   in traditional OSs, users and groups are used for access and permissions when a process is started by a user, the owner of the process will be that user file access and ownership is governed by users and groups each user has their own home directory (usually) and it can be find in /home/username in most distros system uses UIDs (user IDs) to manage users but humans use usernames groups are just collections of users; system assigns them GIDs (group IDs) in linux, there are non-human users too; these users run system processes (daemons) one of the most important users is root or superuser  root is the most powerful user on the system root can access any file/dir and kill any process don&amp;rsquo;t want to be root all the time as that is dangerous if possible, run a command as root via sudo (superuser do)    root #   use su or su - to get a root shell (su is for substitute user)  this can used with a username to act as that user, not just root   who can use sudo?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://wiki.victorbilgin.com/docs/linux/ssh/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://wiki.victorbilgin.com/docs/linux/ssh/</guid>
      <description>SSH #  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://wiki.victorbilgin.com/docs/networking/home-network/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://wiki.victorbilgin.com/docs/networking/home-network/</guid>
      <description>Home Network #  IP Address Scheme #  VLAN 1 (Production) - 10.0.1.0/24 #  Static IPs #   Router1 - 10.0.1.1 Switch1 - 10.0.1.2 AP1 - 10.0.1.3 Printer1 - 10.0.1.4 PI-4 - 10.0.1.5 NAS1 - 10.0.1.50 ubuntu-dev - 10.0.1.51  DHCP Range #  10.0.1.200 - 10.0.1.254
VLAN 2 (Lab) - 10.0.2.0/24 #  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://wiki.victorbilgin.com/docs/recipes/alcoholic/black-russian/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://wiki.victorbilgin.com/docs/recipes/alcoholic/black-russian/</guid>
      <description>Black Russian #  Ingredients #   1½ ounces vodka ¾ ounce Kahlúa (or Tia Maria) Lemon twist  Steps #   Shake the liquid ingredients vigorously with ice. Strain into an ice-filled old-fashioned glass. Twist the lemon peel over the drink, and drop it in.  Variations #  For a Black Magic, add a dash of fresh lemon juice.
For a White Russian, float ½ ounce heavy cream on top.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://wiki.victorbilgin.com/docs/recipes/alcoholic/lemon-drop/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://wiki.victorbilgin.com/docs/recipes/alcoholic/lemon-drop/</guid>
      <description>Lemon Drop #  Ingredients #   2 oz (60ml) vodka .75 oz (45ml) fresh lemon juice .75 oz (45ml) simple syrup  Steps #   Combine all ingredients into a shaker tin with ice Shake and then double strain into a chilled coupe glass Garnish with a lemon twist  Source #  https://www.cocktailchemistrylab.com/home/vodka-cocktails?rq=vodka</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://wiki.victorbilgin.com/docs/recipes/alcoholic/moscow-mule/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://wiki.victorbilgin.com/docs/recipes/alcoholic/moscow-mule/</guid>
      <description>Moscow Mule #  Ingredients #   2oz (60ml) vodka Juice from half a lime 4oz (120ml) ginger beer  Steps #   Add vodka to a collins glass with ice Squeeze in fresh lime juice Top with ginger beer Garnish with a lime wedge  Source #  https://www.cocktailchemistrylab.com/home/vodka-cocktails?rq=vodka</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://wiki.victorbilgin.com/docs/recipes/alcoholic/screwdriver/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://wiki.victorbilgin.com/docs/recipes/alcoholic/screwdriver/</guid>
      <description>Screwdriver #  Ingredients #   2 ounces vodka 4 to 6 ounces fresh orange juice Orange slice  Steps #   Pour the vodka and orange juice into an ice-filled highball glass, and stir. Garnish with the orange slice.  Source #  The Ultimate Bar Book</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://wiki.victorbilgin.com/docs/recipes/alcoholic/the-naughty-dog/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://wiki.victorbilgin.com/docs/recipes/alcoholic/the-naughty-dog/</guid>
      <description>The Naughty Dog #  Ingredients #   1oz Kahlua 1.5oz Rum ~2.5oz Root Beer Float of heavy cream Nutmeg  Steps #   Pour Kahlua into tall glass Add rum Add ice to top Float heavy cream Stir briefly Garnish with nutmeg  Source #  Erick Castro</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
